<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/4.9" created="2017-11-21 18:02" -->
<!-- meaningless addition -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>Respirators 101</title>
	<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com</link>
	<description></description>
	<pubDate>Tue, 21 Nov 2017 18:02:31 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com</wp:base_blog_url>

	<wp:author><wp:author_id>3</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[Livvy]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[octoberblonde92@gmail.com]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Olivia Howard]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[Olivia]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[Howard]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>


	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=4.9</generator>

	<item>
		<title>Who Should Use It</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/11/who-should-use-it/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 18:34:16 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=7</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<ul>
 	<li>Workers</li>
 	<li>Employers</li>
 	<li>Respirator program administrators</li>
</ul>
<img class="alignnone  wp-image-203" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/5838532293_65ed644884_z-300x233.jpg" alt="" width="336" height="261" />

This mobile app aims to make the process of choosing the correct respirator easier and faster.

It is based on the NIOSH Respirator Selection Logic (RSL). Like a logic flow diagram, or a “wizard,” each question helps to narrow down the available options.

&nbsp;]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>7</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:34:16]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:34:16]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[who-should-use-it]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="getting-started"><![CDATA[Getting Started]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>How To Use It</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/11/how-to-use-it/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 18:39:50 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=96</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The respirator selection tool contains a series of questions to help you choose the class of respirator to use in a setting with airborne contaminants. Recommendations are based primarily on contaminants’ physical, chemical, and toxicological properties. Other considerations include filtration efficiency, air supply capability, leakage danger, and face seal characteristics.

Respirator classes are consistent with respirator certification groupings as specified in the NIOSH Guide to the Selection and Use of Particulate Respirators (Certified Under 42 CFR 84).

<img class="alignnone  wp-image-211" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/pexels-photo-583389-300x200.jpeg" alt="" width="439" height="292" />
<blockquote>The recommended respirator class is based on the minimum acceptable degree of protection. NIOSH recommends using respirators with greater protective properties when available.</blockquote>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>96</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:39:50]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:39:50]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[how-to-use-it]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="getting-started"><![CDATA[Getting Started]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Before You Start</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/11/before-you-start/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 18:42:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=98</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Before using the selection tool, you need:
<ol>
 	<li>The name of the contaminant. The search function uses chemical names, CAS numbers, or RTECS numbers.</li>
 	<li>The latest time-weighted average (TWA) of the contaminant at your worksite.</li>
</ol>
<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-200" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/7023032415_4c2b68820c_z-1-300x208.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="208" />

The selection tool will provide data about the contaminant’s properties. This data is drawn from the NIOSH Pocket Guide to Chemical Hazards and OSHA Tables Z-1, Z-2, or Z-3. Data includes:
<ul>
 	<li>Synonyms</li>
 	<li>Immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH) concentration levels</li>
 	<li>Exposure Limits (PELs, RELs, STELs, Ceiling Limits)</li>
 	<li>Eye and Skin Hazards</li>
</ul>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>98</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:42:59]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-11 18:42:59]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[before-you-start]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="getting-started"><![CDATA[Getting Started]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Top 10 Terms To Know</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/11/top-10-terms-to-know/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 11 Nov 2017 19:16:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=100</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Exposure Limits"]PEL: Permissible Exposure Limit. OSHA’s permissible exposure limits establish the maximum level of a specific airborne hazard that an employee can be exposed to, averaged over an 8-hour workday.

REL: Recommended Exposure Limit. The NIOSH Recommended Exposure Limit is a non-mandatory, recommended occupational exposure limit.The OSHA PEL is the legally enforceable regulatory limit. Employers are required to take actions to reduce worker exposures if air samples show levels above OSHA's calculated PEL. However, because OSHA recognizes that many of its PELs are outdated and inadequate measures of worker safety, both OSHA and NIOSH recommend that employers take actions to keep worker exposures below the NIOSH REL.

STEL: Short Term Exposure Limit. Short-term exposure limits are concentrations above which a worker should not be exposed, averaged over 15 minutes. Exposures cannot be repeated more than 4 times per day

TLV: Threshold Limit Value. An occupational exposure level recommended by ACGIH. TLVs are the maximum average airborne concentration of a hazardous material to which healthy adult workers can be exposed during an 8-hour workday and 40-hour workweek—over a working lifetime—without experiencing significant adverse health effects.[/expand]

[expand title="APF"]The Assigned Protection Factor (APF) indicates the workplace level of respiratory protection that a respirator or class of respirators is expected to provide to employees when the employer implements a continuing, effective respiratory protection program as specified by this section.[/expand]

[expand title="MUC"]Maximum Use Concentration (MUC) is the maximum atmospheric concentration of a hazardous substance from which an employee can be expected to be protected when wearing a respirator, and is determined by the assigned protection factor of the respirator or class of respirators and the exposure limit of the hazardous substance. The MUC can be determined mathematically by multiplying the assigned protection factor specified for a respirator by the required OSHA permissible exposure limit, short-term exposure limit, or ceiling limit. When no OSHA exposure limit is available for a hazardous substance, an employer must determine an MUC on the basis of relevant available information and informed professional judgment.[/expand]

[expand title="TWA"]Time-Weighted Average is used to measure a worker's daily exposure to hazardous substances, averaged on an 8-hour workday. The average is calculated from air samples  throughout a work cycle and the amount of time spent working in those conditions. OSHA uses TWAs to establish Permissible Exposure Limits for the contaminants encountered in industries.  The TWA is calculated in units of parts per million (ppm) or mg/m3.[/expand]

[expand title="Ceiling"]Ceiling limits are concentrations above which a worker should never be exposed.[/expand]

[expand title="Oxygen-Deficient Atmosphere"]An atmosphere with oxygen content below 19.5% by volume.Immediately Dangerous to Life or HealthAn atmosphere that poses an immediate threat to life, would cause irreversible adverse health effects, or would impair an individual’s ability to escape from a dangerous atmosphere.[/expand]

[expand title="Loose fit vs. Tight fit"]A Loose-fitting facepiece is designed to form a partial seal with the face.

A Tight-fitting facepiece forms a complete seal with the face.[/expand]

[expand title="Negative vs. Positive Pressure Systems"]Respirators operate either as:

• Negative pressure systems

• Positive pressure systems

During inhalation negative pressure respirators have lower air pressure inside the facepiece compared to the air pressure outside. If the facepiece-to-face seal leaks on these types of respirators, air contaminants will be drawn into the breathing air. All respirators without a supplied-air component are considered negative pressure respirators.

Positive pressure respirators maintain positive air pressure inside the facepiece at all times by means of supplied air. Therefore the air pressure inside the facepiece remains greater than the air pressure outside the facepiece. Thus, any leakage around the facepiece seal should result in air escaping from inside the facepiece to the outside environment rather than worksite contaminants leaking into the facepiece.[/expand]

[expand title="Filter series and Filter efficiency"]Air-purifying respirators that filter out at least 95% of airborne particles during “worst case” testing are given a 95 rating for filter efficiency. Those that filter out at least 99% receive a “99” rating. And those that filter at least 99.97% (essentially 100%) receive a “100” rating.

Air-purifying respirators are rated in a filter series as N, R, or P for protection against oils. This rating is important in industry because some industrial oils can degrade the filter performance so it doesn’t filter properly. Respirators are rated “N,” if they are Not resistant to oil, “R” if somewhat Resistant to oil, and “P” if strongly resistant (oil Proof).NIOSH uses very high standards to test and approve respirators for occupational uses. NIOSH-approved disposable respirators are marked with the manufacturer’s name, the part number (P/N), the protection provided by the filter (e.g., N-95), and “NIOSH.” This information is printed on the facepiece, exhalation valve cover, or head straps.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>100</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-11 19:16:23]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-11 19:16:23]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[top-10-terms-to-know]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="getting-started"><![CDATA[Getting Started]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Purpose of Respirators</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/purpose-of-respirators/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 15:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=108</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Respirators protect employees from inhaling harmful substances, including chemical, biological, and radiological agents. These may come in the form of airborne vapors, gases, dust, fogs, fumes, mists, smokes, or sprays. There are also hazards associated with oxygen deprivation.

Ordinarily, there are a wide range of engineering or workplace controls put in place to eliminate or reduce such dangers. But in some cases certain routine operations and emergency situation may require the use of personal protective equipment and/or respirators.

<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-217" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/building-joy-planning-plans-300x200.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="200" />

Note that respirators only provide protection from respiratory hazards when they are properly selected and used in compliance with the OSHA Respiratory Protection Standard, 29 CFR 1910.134.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>108</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 15:11:09]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 15:11:09]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[purpose-of-respirators]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Types of Respirators</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/types-of-respirators/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 15:49:29 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=110</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Overview"] There are 2 main categories/types of respirators:
<ol>
 	<li>Air-Purifying (e.g. particulate masks, gas/vapor masks, PAPRs)</li>
 	<li>Atmosphere-Supplying (e.g. SCBA, SAR)</li>
</ol>
<h6>Air-Purifying Respirators (or APRs)</h6>
Includes particulate masks, gas/vapor masks, and Powered Air-Purifying Respirators (PAPRs).These use filters or sorbents to remove harmful substances from the air. They range from simple disposable masks to sophisticated devices. They do not supply oxygen and must not be used in oxygen-deficient atmospheres or in other atmospheres that are immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH). Respirators in this family are rated as N, R, or P for protection against oils.

<img class="alignnone wp-image-29" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/FullfacemaskRespirator.jpg" alt="" width="165" height="165" /> <img class="alignnone wp-image-205" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/3m-full-face-respirators-masks-8246pa1-a-64_1000-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="239" height="239" /> <img class="alignnone wp-image-206" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/770030-2-300x232.jpg" alt="" width="239" height="185" />
<h6>Atmosphere-Supplying Respirators</h6>
Includes supplied-air respirators (SARs) and self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA) units.These are designed to provide breathable air from a clean air source other than the surrounding contaminated work atmosphere.

<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-207" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/Комбинированный_СИЗОД_ШР_и_АДА-156x300.jpg" alt="" width="156" height="300" /> <img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-30" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/FullFaceSAR-266x300.jpg" alt="" width="266" height="300" />[/expand]

[expand title="Particulate Respirators (APR)"]

Particulate respirators are a kind of air-purifying respirator. They filter out airborne particles, but not gases or vapors. They can also filter airborne biological agents (e.g. bacteria, viruses) since they are particles.*
Particulate respirators can either be disposable or reusable/elastomeric. They are usually rated as N, R, or P for protection against oils.
<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-208" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/HTB1qVk5JVXXXXcKXXXXq6xXFXXXi-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="300" />
* Selection of respirators for infectious disease and terrorism-related exposures requires consideration of additional factors in addition to the traditional exposure assessment approaches described in this guidance. See the NIOSH respirator topic page http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/respirators/ for additional information and guidance on particular infectious disease and terrorism issues.[/expand]

[expand title="Gas/Vapor Respirators (APR)"] Gas (or vapor) respirators are a kind of tight-fitting air-purifying respirator. They filter chemical gases out of the air as you breathe using cartridge filters. Cartridge filters are specialized and must be selected according to the hazards faced. There is no "all-in-one" filter that protects against everything. The filters are usually rated as N, R, or P for protection against oils.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-31" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/GasVaporRespirator.gif" alt="" width="117" height="109" />[/expand]

[expand title="Combination Particulate and Gas/Vapor Respirators (APR)"]Combination respirators are a kind of <u>tight-fitting air-purifying respirator</u>. They use cartridge filter to filter out both airborne particles and gases as you breathe. Cartridge filters are specialized and must be selected according to the hazards faced. There is no "all-in-one" filter that protects against everything. The filters are usually rated as N, R, or P for protection against oils.

<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-209" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/disposable-half-mask-series-5000-organic-gas-p2-particulates-ffa1-p2-rd-code-5174-675-p_1-288x300.jpg" alt="" width="288" height="300" />[/expand]

[expand title="PAPR (APR)"]A Powered Air-Purifying Respirator (PAPR) can filter particulates, gases, or a combination. Powered air is pulled through the filters and then pushed into the user’s facepiece. There are many varieties of PAPRs, including loose-fitting full face, tight-fitting full face, or half-mask. It can include a helmet or hood.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-39" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/LoosePARP.jpg" alt="" width="199" height="250" /> <img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-38" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/HoodLoosePARP.jpg" alt="" width="191" height="250" />[/expand]

[expand title="SCBA"]A SCBA is a Self-Contained Breathing Apparatus. It is a kind of tight-fitting atmosphere-supplying respirator. Breathing air is supplied to the facepeice from a cylinder of compressed air. The cylinders are carried by the respirator user, often on the back. These respirators provide the highest level of respiratory protection.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-41" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/OSHASCBA.jpg" alt="" width="197" height="250" /> [/expand]

[expand title="SAR"]A SAR is a Supplied-Air Respirator (or airline respirator). It is a kind of atmosphere-supplying respirator. Breathing air is supplied to the facepiece via an airline. The source of breathing air is not carried by the user.

<img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-30" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/FullFaceSAR-266x300.jpg" alt="" width="266" height="300" /> <img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-32" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/HalfFaceSAR-243x300.jpg" alt="" width="243" height="300" /> <img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-33" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/HalfFaceSARwithHat.jpg" alt="" width="169" height="150" /> <img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-40" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/OSHASAR.jpg" alt="" width="199" height="250" />[/expand]

[expand title="Escape Respirators"]A SAR is a Supplied-Air Respirator (or airline respirator). It is a kind of atmosphere-supplying respirator. Breathing air is supplied to the facepiece viaEscape respirators are only for emergency exits. They should allow a person working in a normally safe environment time to escape from sudden hazardous conditions. These respirators are selected based on the time needed to escape and the likelihood of IDLH or oxygen deficiency conditions, not specific APF ratings.
Escape devices can be either APRs or SCBAs.
an airline. The source of breathing air is not carried by the user.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>110</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 15:49:29]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 15:49:29]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[types-of-respirators]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Respirator Characteristics</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/respirator-characteristics/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 16:24:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=116</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Oil Characteristics"]Air-purifying respirators are rated as N, R, or P according to their protection against oils. This rating is important because some industrial oils degrade filters. Air-purifying respirators are rated as N, R, or P according to their protection against oils. This rating is important because some industrial oils degrade filters.
<ul>
 	<li>N= <strong>N</strong>ot resistant to oil</li>
 	<li>R= somewhat <strong>R</strong>esistant to oil</li>
 	<li>P= strongly resistant, or oil <strong>P</strong>roof</li>
</ul>
You will often find this letter rating alongside the percentage of particulate filtration protection that the respirator offers (usually 95%, 99%, or 99.7%). The rating would look something like, “N99” or “P95”.[/expand]

[expand title="Quarter-face, Half-face, and Full-face"]Respirators can be either:
<ul>
 	<li>Quarter-face respirators, where just the top of the nose and chin are covered</li>
 	<li>Half-face respirators, where the whole nose and down around the chin are covered</li>
 	<li>Full-face respirators, where the whole face, at least up to the hairline and down around the chin are covered. Sometimes the whole head is covered.</li>
</ul>
A full face respirator provides a higher level of protection than half-facepiece respirator because it has better sealing characteristics. Since it covers the user's eyes and face, it can also be used to protect against liquid splashes and irritating vapors.[/expand]

[expand title="Hoods and Helmets"]Eye protection is often required in addition to respiratory protection when working with airborne particles and chemicals. Full facepiece respirators are used to provide eye protection. Full-face coverage is often integrated with a hood or helmet to provide better insulation from various hazards (e.g. falling material, etc.)[/expand]

[expand title="Loose fitting vs. Tight fitting"]Respirators can be either:
<ul>
 	<li>Tight-fitting</li>
 	<li>Loose-fitting</li>
</ul>
Tight-fitting respirators create a tight seal between the respirator and the face and/or neck of the respirator user. If the respirator's seal leaks, contaminated air will be pulled into the facepiece, endangering the user. If you are required to use a tight-fitting respirator at work, you must be fit tested with the respirator selected for your use. You also must perform regular user seal checks. This check determines if the respirator is properly sealed to the face or needs to be readjusted.
Loose-fitting respirators do not depend on a tight seal with the face to provide protection. Therefore, they do not need to be fit tested.

<img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-40" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/OSHASAR.jpg" alt="" width="199" height="250" /> <img class="alignnone size-full wp-image-39" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/LoosePARP.jpg" alt="" width="199" height="250" /> <img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-32" src="http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/wp-content/uploads/2017/11/HalfFaceSAR-243x300.jpg" alt="" width="243" height="300" />

Loose fitting full-face PARPs vs. Tight fitting half-face SAR[/expand]

[expand title="Negative vs. Positive Pressure Systems"]Respirators operate either as:
<ul>
 	<li>Negative pressure systems</li>
 	<li>Positive pressure systems</li>
</ul>
During inhalation negative pressure respirators have lower air pressure inside the facepiece compared to the air pressure outside. If the facepiece-to-face seal leaks on these types of respirators, air contaminants will be drawn into the breathing air. All respirators without a supplied-air component are considered negative pressure respirators.
Positive pressure respirators maintain positive air pressure inside the facepiece at all times by means of supplied air. Therefore the air pressure inside the facepiece remains greater than the air pressure outside the facepiece. Thus, any leakage around the facepiece seal should result in air escaping from inside the facepiece to the outside environment rather than worksite contaminants leaking into the facepiece.[/expand]

[expand title="Positive Pressure Modes"]There are three modes that positive pressure respirators operate in:
<ul>
 	<li>Demand mode</li>
 	<li>Pressure demand mode</li>
 	<li>Continuous flow mode</li>
</ul>
Demand mode means that air only flows into the mask when you inhale. This system would allow outside air in if there was a breach around the seal of the respirator, because the pressure is lower inside the mask during inhalation. This affects the protection factors of the respirator. Pressure demand mode means that throughout the breathing cycle the supplied air regulator works to maintain positive pressure inside of the respirator. If there is a breach in the seal of the respirator, the air inside of the respirator will escape from where the breach is not allowing outside air to enter.
Continuous flow mode means that a continuous stream of air is blown into the facepiece at all times.
If the respirator also has filters or cartridges is important to choose filters that have the appropriate APF for the mode in which the respirator will be operating.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>116</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 16:24:03]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 16:24:03]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[respirator-characteristics]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Caring For Your Respirator</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/caring-for-your-respirator/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 17:36:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=119</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Caring for your respirator"]
Respirator care is a vital part of any respiratory protection program. Regularly caring for your respirator ensures that it is always in good working condition and capable of offering the protection you need for your job.[/expand]

[expand title="Employer"]
Employers are required to establish procedures and regular maintenance schedules for the care of all respirators used by their employees (unless they are voluntary respirators). This includes procedures for the cleaning, storing, inspecting, and repairing or disposing of respirators.
Care must always be done in accordance with OSHA requirements, but manufacturers’ directions should also be considered, as there may be cleaning solutions that should not be used on certain types of respirators.[/expand]

[expand title="Regular care"]
Respirators should always be inspected for damage before and after use. Pay particular attention to:
Basic functionality (user fit test)
Connections (check tightness)
Facepiece
Head straps
Valves
Tubes
Hoses
Any cartridges, canisters, or filters
Elastomeric parts (check for pliability, signs of deterioration)[/expand]

[expand title="Damage"]
Remove any damaged respirators form use to either be discarded or repaired by a trained person. If your respirator fails an inspection or is defective, your employer must remove it from service and either repair it or discard it. Repairs must be made according to the respirator manufacturer's instructions and must use only NIOSH-approved parts that are designed for the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Storage"]
It is important for respirators to be stored properly to protect them from damage or contamination. Sunlight, extreme temperatures, excessive moisture, and some chemicals can all damage respirators. Always store your respirator in a way that prevents deforming the facepiece or exhalation valve. Never leave your respirator hanging on a machine, lying on your workbench, tucked into your pocket, or tossed into your toolbox or a drawer.[/expand]

[expand title="Changing filters"]
Always change filters on schedule. If you use a respirator for protection against gases and vapors, your employer must determine a schedule for replacing worn out cartridges or canisters. This is known as a "change-out schedule." Your employer is responsible for providing this information to you, so that you know when a cartridge or canister must be changed.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>119</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:36:06]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:36:06]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[caring-for-your-respirator]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Respirator Safety</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/respirator-safety/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 17:44:09 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=121</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Overview"]Respirators only provide protection from respiratory hazards when they are properly selected and used in compliance with the Respiratory Protection standard (29 CFR 1910.134 and 29 CFR 1926.103). It is imperative to choose the right respirator for the job and to maintain the respirator so that it continues to provide optimum protection from the hazards of the worksite.[/expand]

[expand title="Eye Irritation"]Eye protecting full facepieces, helmets, or hoods are required for routine exposures to airborne contaminants that cause any eye irritation. When data on threshold levels for eye irritation are insufficient, quarter or half-mask respirators can be used, as long as the worker has no eye discomfort. For escape, some eye irritation is permissible if the severity of irritation does not inhibit the escape and if no irreversible damage is likely.[/expand]

[expand title="When to leave"]<strong>If you detect any odor while wearing your respirator, get out immediately.</strong>

Employers are required to provide a “safe area” in the workplace where workers can safely remove their respirators to wash or conduct maintenance on them. You should never adjust a respirator in the contaminated work area. Always go to the safe area before removing your respirator.

Other reasons you may need to leave the work area include:
<ul>
 	<li>If you need to wash your face or the respirator facepiece to prevent eye or skin irritation associated with respirator use.</li>
 	<li>If you detect vapor or gas breaking through (the filter may need changed).</li>
 	<li>If you notice that the facepiece is leaking.</li>
 	<li>If you observe a change in breathing resistance (the filter may need changed).</li>
 	<li>If the respirator or parts of the respirator, such as valves or straps, are not working properly and need to be replaced.</li>
</ul>
[/expand]
[expand title="Kinds of Hazards Encountered"]Airborne vapors, gases, dust, fogs, fumes, fibers, mists, smokes, or sprays all can carry or contain hazardous substances and present serious dangers to workers who inhale them. There are also hazardous atmospheres such as low-oxygen atmospheres that can endanger the life of the employee. Respirators protect against many of these dangers.[/expand]

[expand title="User Seal Check"]User seal checks are a quick and easy way for employees to verify that they have put on their respirators correctly and that the respirators are working properly. A user seal check is NOT a kind of fit testing.

To conduct a user seal check, the employee performs a negative or positive pressure fit check, depending on what kind of respirator they’re using.

For the negative pressure check, the employee:
<ul>
 	<li>covers the respirator inlets (cartridges, canisters, or seals)</li>
 	<li>gently inhales, and</li>
 	<li>holds breath for 10 seconds.The facepiece should collapse on the worker’s face and remain collapsed.</li>
</ul>
For the positive pressure check, the worker:
<ul>
 	<li>covers the respirator exhalation valve(s), and</li>
 	<li>exhales.</li>
</ul>
The facepiece should hold the positive pressure for a few seconds. During this time, the employee should not hear or feel the air leaking out of the face-to-facepiece seal.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>121</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:44:09]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:44:09]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[respirator-safety]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Fit-Testing</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/fit-testing/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 17:48:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=123</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Overview"]There are two kinds of fit-testing:
<ul>
 	<li>Qualitative</li>
 	<li>Quantitative</li>
</ul>
Fit testing is used to determine how well a respirator “fits”—that is, whether the respirator forms a seal on the user’s face. If there’s not a good facepiece-to-face seal, the respirator will provide a lower level of protection than it was rated for. The <u>APFs</u> only apply if the respirators are properly selected and used in compliance with the full respirator program, including initial fit testing. Fit testing must be performed before initial use and then at least once a year. <u>The Respiratory Protection standard</u> requires employers to conduct fit testing on all employees who are required to wear a respirator that includes a <u>tight-fitting</u> facepiece.[/expand]

[expand title="Quantitative fit test (QNFT)"]Quantitative fit testing is a method of measuring the amount of leakage into a respirator. It is a numeric assessment of how well a respirator fits a particular individual. To quantitatively fit test a respirator, sampling probes or other measuring devices must be placed to measure aerosol concentrations both outside and on the inside of the respirator facepiece. The respirator wearer then performs the usual <u>user seal checks.</u>[/expand]

[expand title="Qualitative fit test (QLFT)"]Qualitative fit testing is a pass/fail test that relies on the respirator wearer’s response to a substance (“test agent”) used in the test to determine respirator fit.In qualitative fit testing, after performing user seal checks, the respirator wearer stands in an enclosure and a test agent is introduced.If the individual can detect the test agent, this indicates that the agent leaked into the facepiece and that the respirator has failed the test because a good facepiece-to- face seal has not been achieved.[/expand]

[expand title="When to fit-test"]Fit testing must be conducted for all employees required to wear <u>tight-fitting</u> facepiece respirators as follows:
<ul>
 	<li>Prior to initial use.</li>
 	<li>Whenever an employee switches to a different tightfitting facepiece respirator (for example, a different size, make or model).</li>
 	<li>At least annually.</li>
</ul>
[/expand]
[expand title="Fit Testing Atmosphere- Supplying Respirators"]All fit testing conducted for <u>tight-fitting atmosphere-supplying respirators</u> and <u>powered air-purifying respirators</u> must be conducted in the <u>negative pressure</u> mode, even if the respirator will be used with <u>positive</u> pressure. This is because it is difficult outside of a laboratory test situation to accurately perform fit testing on positive pressure respirators.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>123</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:48:20]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:48:20]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[fit-testing]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Employer Responsibilites</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/employer-responsibilites/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 17:55:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=128</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<ul>
 	<li>The standard requires your employer to do the following:
develop and implement a written respiratory protection program</li>
 	<li>evaluate the respiratory hazards in the workplace</li>
 	<li>select and provide appropriate respirators</li>
 	<li>provide worker medical evaluations and respirator fit testing</li>
 	<li>provide for the maintenance, storage and cleaning of respirators</li>
 	<li>provide worker training about respiratory hazards and proper respirator use</li>
 	<li>evaluate workers' use of respirators and correct any problems</li>
 	<li>provide you with access to specific records and documents, such as a written copy of your employer's respiratory protection program</li>
</ul>
(<a href="https://www.osha.gov/video/respiratory_protection/construction_transcript.html">https://www.osha.gov/video/respiratory_protection/construction_transcript.html</a>)]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>128</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:55:22]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:55:22]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[employer-responsibilites]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="all-about-respirators"><![CDATA[All About Respirators]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Conversion Tables</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/conversion-tables/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 17:57:55 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=132</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[PEL x APF = MUC
TWA:
(xppm)(xhours) + (xppm)(xhours)… = ttl ppm = TWAppm/8hours
ttl hours

TWA equation: TWA= (t1c1+t2c2+…+tncn) / (t1+t2+…+tn)

t=time of exposure
c= concentration level during the time period
The TWA is calculated in units of parts per million (ppm) or mg/m3.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>132</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:57:55]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 17:57:55]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[conversion-tables]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="conversion-tables"><![CDATA[Conversion Tables]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>OSHA Standards</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/osha-standards/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 18:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=134</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This section applies to General Industry (part 1910), Shipyards (part 1915), Marine Terminals (part 1917), Longshoring (part 1918), and Construction (part 1926). [display-posts tag="OSHA-Standards" posts_per_page="15"]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>134</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:00:20]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:00:20]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[osha-standards]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134  (A) PERMISSIBLE PRACTICE</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134-a-permissible-practice/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 18:02:46 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=136</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="1910.134(a)(1) Controlling Hazards"]
In the control of those occupational diseases caused by breathing air contaminated with harmful dusts, fogs, fumes, mists, gases, smokes, sprays, or vapors, the primary objective shall be to prevent atmospheric contamination. This shall be accomplished as far as feasible by accepted engineering control measures (for example, enclosure or confinement of the operation, general and local ventilation, and substitution of less toxic materials). When effective engineering controls are not feasible, or while they are being instituted, appropriate respirators shall be used pursuant to this section.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(a)(2) Employer Responsibilities"]
A respirator shall be provided to each employee when such equipment is necessary to protect the health of such employee. The employer shall provide the respirators which are applicable and suitable for the purpose intended. The employer shall be responsible for the establishment and maintenance of a respiratory protection program, which shall include the requirements outlined in paragraph (c) of this section. The program shall cover each employee required by this section to use a respirator.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>136</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:02:46]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:02:46]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134-a-permissible-practice]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(B) DEFINITIONS</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134b-definitions/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 18:10:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=139</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The following definitions are important terms used in the respiratory protection standard in this section.

[expand title="Air-purifying respirator"]
Air-purifying respirator means a respirator with an air-purifying filter, cartridge, or canister that removes specific air contaminants by passing ambient air through the air-purifying element.[/expand]

[expand title="Assigned protection factor (APF)"]
Assigned protection factor (APF) means the workplace level of respiratory protection that a respirator or class of respirators is expected to provide to employees when the employer implements a continuing, effective respiratory protection program as specified by this section.[/expand]

[expand title="Atmosphere-supplying respirator"]
Atmosphere-supplying respirator means a respirator that supplies the respirator user with breathing air from a source independent of the ambient atmosphere, and includes supplied-air respirators (SARs) and self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA) units.[/expand]

[expand title="Canister or cartridge"]
Canister or cartridge means a container with a filter, sorbent, or catalyst, or combination of these items, which removes specific contaminants from the air passed through the container.[/expand]

[expand title="Demand respirator"]
Demand respirator means an atmosphere-supplying respirator that admits breathing air to the facepiece only when a negative pressure is created inside the facepiece by inhalation.[/expand]

[expand title="Emergency situation"]
Emergency situation means any occurrence such as, but not limited to, equipment failure, rupture of containers, or failure of control equipment that may or does result in an uncontrolled significant release of an airborne contaminant.[/expand]

[expand title="Employee exposure"]
Employee exposure means exposure to a concentration of an airborne contaminant that would occur if the employee were not using respiratory protection.[/expand]

[expand title="End-of-service-life indicator (ESLI)"]
End-of-service-life indicator (ESLI) means a system that warns the respirator user of the approach of the end of adequate respiratory protection, for example, that the sorbent is approaching saturation or is no longer effective.[/expand]

[expand title="Escape-only respirator"]
Escape-only respirator means a respirator intended to be used only for emergency exit.[/expand]

[expand title="Filter or air purifying element"]
Filter or air purifying element means a component used in respirators to remove solid or liquid aerosols from the inspired air.[/expand]

[expand title="Filtering facepiece (dust mask)"]
Filtering facepiece (dust mask) means a negative pressure particulate respirator with a filter as an integral part of the facepiece or with the entire facepiece composed of the filtering medium.[/expand]

[expand title="Fit factor"]
Fit factor means a quantitative estimate of the fit of a particular respirator to a specific individual, and typically estimates the ratio of the concentration of a substance in ambient air to its concentration inside the respirator when worn.[/expand]

[expand title="Fit test"]
Fit test means the use of a protocol to qualitatively or quantitatively evaluate the fit of a respirator on an individual. (See also Qualitative fit test QLFT and Quantitative fit test QNFT.)[/expand]

[expand title="Helmet"]
Helmet means a rigid respiratory inlet covering that also provides head protection against impact and penetration.[/expand]

[expand title="High efficiency particulate air (HEPA)"]
High efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter means a filter that is at least 99.97% efficient in removing monodisperse particles of 0.3 micrometers in diameter. The equivalent NIOSH 42 CFR 84 particulate filters are the N100, R100, and P100 filters.[/expand]

[expand title="Hood"]
Hood means a respiratory inlet covering that completely covers the head and neck and may also cover portions of the shoulders and torso.[/expand]

[expand title="Immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH)"]
Immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH) means an atmosphere that poses an immediate threat to life, would cause irreversible adverse health effects, or would impair an individual's ability to escape from a dangerous atmosphere.[/expand]

[expand title="Interior structural firefighting"]
Interior structural firefighting means the physical activity of fire suppression, rescue or both, inside of buildings or enclosed structures which are involved in a fire situation beyond the incipient stage. (See 29 CFR 1910.155)[/expand]

[expand title="Loose-fitting facepiece"]
Loose-fitting facepiece means a respiratory inlet covering that is designed to form a partial seal with the face.[/expand]

[expand title="Maximum use concentration (MUC)"]
Maximum use concentration (MUC) means the maximum atmospheric concentration of a hazardous substance from which an employee can be expected to be protected when wearing a respirator, and is determined by the assigned protection factor of the respirator or class of respirators and the exposure limit of the hazardous substance. The MUC can be determined mathematically by multiplying the assigned protection factor specified for a respirator by the required OSHA permissible exposure limit, short-term exposure limit, or ceiling limit. When no OSHA exposure limit is available for a hazardous substance, an employer must determine an MUC on the basis of relevant available information and informed professional judgment.[/expand]

[expand title="Negative pressure respirator (tight fitting)"]
Negative pressure respirator (tight fitting) means a respirator in which the air pressure inside the facepiece is negative during inhalation with respect to the ambient air pressure outside the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Oxygen deficient atmosphere"]
Oxygen deficient atmosphere means an atmosphere with an oxygen content below 19.5% by volume.[/expand]

[expand title="Physician or other licensed health care professional (PLHCP)"]
Physician or other licensed health care professional (PLHCP) means an individual whose legally permitted scope of practice (i.e., license, registration, or certification) allows him or her to independently provide, or be delegated the responsibility to provide, some or all of the health care services required by paragraph (e) of this section.[/expand]

[expand title="Positive pressure respirator"]
Positive pressure respirator means a respirator in which the pressure inside the respiratory inlet covering exceeds the ambient air pressure outside the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Powered air-purifying respirator (PAPR)"]
Powered air-purifying respirator (PAPR) means an air-purifying respirator that uses a blower to force the ambient air through air-purifying elements to the inlet covering.[/expand]

[expand title="Pressure demand respirator"]
Pressure demand respirator means a positive pressure atmosphere-supplying respirator that admits breathing air to the facepiece when the positive pressure is reduced inside the facepiece by inhalation.[/expand]

[expand title="Qualitative fit test (QLFT)"]
Qualitative fit test (QLFT) means a pass/fail fit test to assess the adequacy of respirator fit that relies on the individual's response to the test agent.[/expand]

[expand title="Quantitative fit test (QNFT)"]
Quantitative fit test (QNFT) means an assessment of the adequacy of respirator fit by numerically measuring the amount of leakage into the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Respiratory inlet covering"]
Respiratory inlet covering means that portion of a respirator that forms the protective barrier between the user's respiratory tract and an air-purifying device or breathing air source, or both. It may be a facepiece, helmet, hood, suit, or a mouthpiece respirator with nose clamp.[/expand]

[expand title="Self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA)"]
Self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA) means an atmosphere-supplying respirator for which the breathing air source is designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]

[expand title="Service life"]Service life means the period of time that a respirator, filter or sorbent, or other respiratory equipment provides adequate protection to the wearer.[/expand]

[expand title="Supplied-air respirator (SAR)"]
Supplied-air respirator (SAR) or airline respirator means an atmosphere-supplying respirator for which the source of breathing air is not designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]

[expand title="This section"]
This section means this respiratory protection standard.[/expand]

[expand title="Tight-fitting facepiece"]
Tight-fitting facepiece means a respiratory inlet covering that forms a complete seal with the face.[/expand]

[expand title="User seal check"]
User seal check means an action conducted by the respirator user to determine if the respirator is properly seated to the face.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>139</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:10:32]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:10:32]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134b-definitions]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(C) RESPIRATORY PROTECTION PROGRAM</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134c-respiratory-protection-program/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 18:15:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=141</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires the employer to develop and implement a written respiratory protection program with required worksite-specific procedures and elements for required respirator use. The program must be administered by a suitably trained program administrator. In addition, certain program elements may be required for voluntary use to prevent potential hazards associated with the use of the respirator. The Small Entity Compliance Guide contains criteria for the selection of a program administrator and a sample program that meets the requirements of this paragraph. Copies of the Small Entity Compliance Guide will be available on or about April 8, 1998 from the Occupational Safety and Health Administration's Office of Publications, Room N 3101, 200 Constitution Avenue, NW, Washington, DC, 20210 (202-219-4667).

[expand title="1910.134(c)(1) Program Provisions"]
In any workplace where respirators are necessary to protect the health of the employee or whenever respirators are required by the employer, the employer shall establish and implement a written respiratory protection program with worksite-specific procedures. The program shall be updated as necessary to reflect those changes in workplace conditions that affect respirator use. The employer shall include in the program the following provisions of this section, as applicable:
<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(i)</strong>
Procedures for selecting respirators for use in the workplace;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(ii)</strong>
Medical evaluations of employees required to use respirators;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(iii)</strong>
Fit testing procedures for tight-fitting respirators;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(iv)</strong>
Procedures for proper use of respirators in routine and reasonably foreseeable emergency situations;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(v)</strong>
Procedures and schedules for cleaning, disinfecting, storing, inspecting, repairing, discarding, and otherwise maintaining respirators;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(vi)</strong>
Procedures to ensure adequate air quality, quantity, and flow of breathing air for atmosphere-supplying respirators;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(vii)</strong>
Training of employees in the respiratory hazards to which they are potentially exposed during routine and emergency situations;

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(viii)</strong>
Training of employees in the proper use of respirators, including putting on and removing them, any limitations on their use, and their maintenance; and

<strong>1910.134(c)(1)(ix)</strong>
Procedures for regularly evaluating the effectiveness of the program.

[expand title="1910.134(c)(2) Non-Required Respirator Use"]
Where respirator use is not required:
<strong>1910.134(c)(2)(i)</strong>
An employer may provide respirators at the request of employees or permit employees to use their own respirators, if the employer determines that such respirator use will not in itself create a hazard. If the employer determines that any voluntary respirator use is permissible, the employer shall provide the respirator users with the information contained in Appendix D to this section ("Information for Employees Using Respirators When Not Required Under the Standard"); and

<strong>1910.134(c)(2)(ii)</strong>
In addition, the employer must establish and implement those elements of a written respiratory protection program necessary to ensure that any employee using a respirator voluntarily is medically able to use that respirator, and that the respirator is cleaned, stored, and maintained so that its use does not present a health hazard to the user. Exception: Employers are not required to include in a written respiratory protection program those employees whose only use of respirators involves the voluntary use of filtering facepieces (dust masks).[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(c)(3) Program Administrator"]
The employer shall designate a program administrator who is qualified by appropriate training or experience that is commensurate with the complexity of the program to administer or oversee the respiratory protection program and conduct the required evaluations of program effectiveness.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(c)(4) Employer Provisions"]
The employer shall provide respirators, training, and medical evaluations at no cost to the employee.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>141</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:15:04]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 18:15:04]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134c-respiratory-protection-program]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(D) SELECTION OF RESPIRATORS</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134d-selection-of-respirators/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 19:38:54 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=147</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires the employer to evaluate respiratory hazard(s) in the workplace, identify relevant workplace and user factors, and base respirator selection on these factors. The paragraph also specifies appropriately protective respirators for use in IDLH atmospheres, and limits the selection and use of air-purifying respirators.
[expand title="1910.134(d)(1) General Requirements"]

<strong>1910.134(d)(1)(i)</strong>
The employer shall select and provide an appropriate respirator based on the respiratory hazard(s) to which the worker is exposed and workplace and user factors that affect respirator performance and reliability.

<strong>1910.134(d)(1)(ii)</strong>
The employer shall select a NIOSH-certified respirator. The respirator shall be used in compliance with the conditions of its certification.

<strong>1910.134(d)(1)(iii)</strong>
The employer shall identify and evaluate the respiratory hazard(s) in the workplace; this evaluation shall include a reasonable estimate of employee exposures to respiratory hazard(s) and an identification of the contaminant's chemical state and physical form. Where the employer cannot identify or reasonably estimate the employee exposure, the employer shall consider the atmosphere to be IDLH.

<strong>1910.134(d)(1)(iv)</strong>
The employer shall select respirators from a sufficient number of respirator models and sizes so that the respirator is acceptable to, and correctly fits, the user.[/expand]
[expand title="1910.134(d)(2) Respirators for IDLH Atmospheres"]

<strong>1910.134(d)(2)(i)</strong>
The employer shall provide the following respirators for employee use in IDLH atmospheres:

<strong>1910.134(d)(2)(i)(A)</strong>
A full facepiece pressure demand SCBA certified by NIOSH for a minimum service life of thirty minutes, or

<strong>1910.134(d)(2)(i)(B)</strong>
A combination full facepiece pressure demand supplied-air respirator (SAR) with auxiliary self-contained air supply.

<strong>1910.134(d)(2)(ii)</strong>
Respirators provided only for escape from IDLH atmospheres shall be NIOSH-certified for escape from the atmosphere in which they will be used.

<strong>1910.134(d)(2)(iii)</strong>
All oxygen-deficient atmospheres shall be considered IDLH. Exception: If the employer demonstrates that, under all foreseeable conditions, the oxygen concentration can be maintained within the ranges specified in Table II of this section (i.e., for the altitudes set out in the table), then any atmosphere-supplying respirator may be used.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(d)(3) Respirators for non-IDLH Atmospheres"]

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)</strong>
The employer shall provide a respirator that is adequate to protect the health of the employee and ensure compliance with all other OSHA statutory and regulatory requirements, under routine and reasonably foreseeable emergency situations.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)(A)</strong>
Assigned Protection Factors (APFs) Employers must use the assigned protection factors listed in Table 1 to select a respirator that meets or exceeds the required level of employee protection. When using a combination respirator (e.g., airline respirators with an air-purifying filter), employers must ensure that the assigned protection factor is appropriate to the mode of operation in which the respirator is being used.

[table id=1 /]

<strong>Notes:</strong>
[1]Employers may select respirators assigned for use in higher workplace concentrations of a hazardous substance for use at lower concentrations of that substance, or when required respirator use is independent of concentration.
[2]The assigned protection factors in Table 1 are only effective when the employer implements a continuing, effective respirator program as required by this section (29 CFR 1910.134), including training, fit testing, maintenance, and use requirements.
[3]This APF category includes filtering facepieces, and half masks with elastomeric facepieces.
[4]The employer must have evidence provided by the respirator manufacturer that testing of these respirators demonstrates performance at a level of protection of 1,000 or greater to receive an APF of 1,000. This level of performance can best be demonstrated by performing a WPF or SWPF study or equivalent testing. Absent such testing, all other PAPRs and SARs with helmets/hoods are to be treated as loose-fitting facepiece respirators, and receive an APF of 25.
[5]These APFs do not apply to respirators used solely for escape. For escape respirators used in association with specific substances covered by 29 CFR 1910 subpart Z, employers must refer to the appropriate substance-specific standards in that subpart. Escape respirators for other IDLH atmospheres are specified by 29 CFR 1910.134 (d)(2)(ii).

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)(B)</strong>
Maximum Use Concentration (MUC)

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)(B)(1)</strong>
The employer must select a respirator for employee use that maintains the employee's exposure to the hazardous substance, when measured outside the respirator, at or below the MUC.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)(B)(2)</strong>
Employers must not apply MUCs to conditions that are immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH); instead, they must use respirators listed for IDLH conditions in paragraph (d)(2) of this standard.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(i)(B)(3)</strong>
When the calculated MUC exceeds the IDLH level for a hazardous substance, or the performance limits of the cartridge or canister, then employers must set the maximum MUC at that lower limit.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(ii)</strong>
The respirator selected shall be appropriate for the chemical state and physical form of the contaminant.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iii)</strong>
For protection against gases and vapors, the employer shall provide:

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iii)(A)</strong>
An atmosphere-supplying respirator, or

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iii)(B)</strong>
An air-purifying respirator, provided that:

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iii)(B)(1)</strong>
The respirator is equipped with an end-of-service-life indicator (ESLI) certified by NIOSH for the contaminant; or

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iii)(B)(2)</strong>
If there is no ESLI appropriate for conditions in the employer's workplace, the employer implements a change schedule for canisters and cartridges that is based on objective information or data that will ensure that canisters and cartridges are changed before the end of their service life. The employer shall describe in the respirator program the information and data relied upon and the basis for the canister and cartridge change schedule and the basis for reliance on the data.

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iv)</strong>
For protection against particulates, the employer shall provide:

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iv)(A)</strong>
An atmosphere-supplying respirator; or

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iv)(B)</strong>
An air-purifying respirator equipped with a filter certified by NIOSH under 30 CFR part 11 as a high efficiency particulate air (HEPA) filter, or an air-purifying respirator equipped with a filter certified for particulates by NIOSH under 42 CFR part 84; or

<strong>1910.134(d)(3)(iv)(C)</strong>
For contaminants consisting primarily of particles with mass median aerodynamic diameters (MMAD) of at least 2 micrometers, an air-purifying respirator equipped with any filter certified for particulates by NIOSH.

TABLE I. -- ASSIGNED PROTECTION FACTORS
[RESERVED]

[table id=2 /]

[1]Above 8,000 feet the exception does not apply. Oxygen-
enriched breathing air must be supplied above 14,000 feet.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>147</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 19:38:54]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 19:38:54]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134d-selection-of-respirators]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(E) MEDICAL EVALUATION</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134e-medical-evaluation/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 19:59:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=156</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Using a respirator may place a physiological burden on employees that varies with the type of respirator worn, the job and workplace conditions in which the respirator is used, and the medical status of the employee. Accordingly, this paragraph specifies the minimum requirements for medical evaluation that employers must implement to determine the employee's ability to use a respirator.

[expand title="1910.134(e)(1) General"]
The employer shall provide a medical evaluation to determine the employee's ability to use a respirator, before the employee is fit tested or required to use the respirator in the workplace. The employer may discontinue an employee's medical evaluations when the employee is no longer required to use a respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(2) Medical Evaluation Procedures"]
<strong>1910.134(e)(2)(i)</strong>
The employer shall identify a physician or other licensed health care professional (PLHCP) to perform medical evaluations using a medical questionnaire or an initial medical examination that obtains the same information as the medical questionnaire.

<strong>1910.134(e)(2)(ii)</strong>
The medical evaluation shall obtain the information requested by the questionnaire in Sections 1 and 2, Part A of Appendix C of this section.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(3) Follow-up Medical Examination"]
<strong>1910.134(e)(3)(i)</strong>
The employer shall ensure that a follow-up medical examination is provided for an employee who gives a positive response to any question among questions 1 through 8 in Section 2, Part A of Appendix C or whose initial medical examination demonstrates the need for a follow-up medical examination.

<strong>1910.134(e)(3)(ii)</strong>
The follow-up medical examination shall include any medical tests, consultations, or diagnostic procedures that the PLHCP deems necessary to make a final determination.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(4) Admin. of Medical Questionnaire and Examinations"]
<strong>1910.134(e)(4)(i)</strong>
The medical questionnaire and examinations shall be administered confidentially during the employee's normal working hours or at a time and place convenient to the employee. The medical questionnaire shall be administered in a manner that ensures that the employee understands its content.

<strong>1910.134(e)(4)(ii)</strong>
The employer shall provide the employee with an opportunity to discuss the questionnaire and examination results with the PLHCP.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(5) Supplemental Information for the PLHCP"]
<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)</strong>
The following information must be provided to the PLHCP before the PLHCP makes a recommendation concerning an employee's ability to use a respirator:

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)(A)</strong>
(A) The type and weight of the respirator to be used by the employee;

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)(B)</strong>
The duration and frequency of respirator use (including use for rescue and escape);

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)(C)</strong>
The expected physical work effort;

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)(D)</strong>
Additional protective clothing and equipment to be worn; and

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(i)(E)</strong>
Temperature and humidity extremes that may be encountered.

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(ii)</strong>
Any supplemental information provided previously to the PLHCP regarding an employee need not be provided for a subsequent medical evaluation if the information and the PLHCP remain the same.

<strong>1910.134(e)(5)(iii)</strong>
The employer shall provide the PLHCP with a copy of the written respiratory protection program and a copy of this section.

Note to Paragraph (e)(5)(iii): When the employer replaces a PLHCP, the employer must ensure that the new PLHCP obtains this information, either by providing the documents directly to the PLHCP or having the documents transferred from the former PLHCP to the new PLHCP. However, OSHA does not expect employers to have employees medically reevaluated solely because a new PLHCP has been selected.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(6) Medical Determination"]
In determining the employee's ability to use a respirator, the employer shall:

<strong>1910.134(e)(6)(i)</strong>
Obtain a written recommendation regarding the employee's ability to use the respirator from the PLHCP. The recommendation shall provide only the following information:

<strong>1910.134(e)(6)(i)(A)</strong>
Any limitations on respirator use related to the medical condition of the employee, or relating to the workplace conditions in which the respirator will be used, including whether or not the employee is medically able to use the respirator;

<strong>1910.134(e)(6)(i)(B)</strong>
The need, if any, for follow-up medical evaluations; and

<strong>1910.134(e)(6)(i)(C)</strong>
A statement that the PLHCP has provided the employee with a copy of the PLHCP's written recommendation.

<strong>1910.134(e)(6)(ii)</strong>
If the respirator is a negative pressure respirator and the PLHCP finds a medical condition that may place the employee's health at increased risk if the respirator is used, the employer shall provide a PAPR if the PLHCP's medical evaluation finds that the employee can use such a respirator; if a subsequent medical evaluation finds that the employee is medically able to use a negative pressure respirator, then the employer is no longer required to provide a PAPR.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(e)(7) Additional Medical Evaluations"]
At a minimum, the employer shall provide additional medical evaluations that comply with the requirements of this section if:

<strong>1910.134(e)(7)(i)</strong>
An employee reports medical signs or symptoms that are related to ability to use a respirator;

<strong>1910.134(e)(7)(ii)</strong>
A PLHCP, supervisor, or the respirator program administrator informs the employer that an employee needs to be reevaluated;

<strong>1910.134(e)(7)(iii)</strong>
Information from the respiratory protection program, including observations made during fit testing and program evaluation, indicates a need for employee reevaluation; or

<strong>1910.134(e)(7)(iv)</strong>
A change occurs in workplace conditions (e.g., physical work effort, protective clothing, temperature) that may result in a substantial increase in the physiological burden placed on an employee.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>156</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 19:59:38]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 19:59:38]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134e-medical-evaluation]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(F) FIT TESTING</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134f-fit-testing/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:07:38 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=159</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires that, before an employee may be required to use any respirator with a negative or positive pressure tight-fitting facepiece, the employee must be fit tested with the same make, model, style, and size of respirator that will be used. This paragraph specifies the kinds of fit tests allowed, the procedures for conducting them, and how the results of the fit tests must be used.

[expand title="1910.134(f)(1) Fit Test Passed"]
The employer shall ensure that employees using a tight-fitting facepiece respirator pass an appropriate qualitative fit test (QLFT) or quantitative fit test (QNFT) as stated in this paragraph.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(f)(2) When to Fit Test"]
The employer shall ensure that an employee using a tight-fitting facepiece respirator is fit tested prior to initial use of the respirator, whenever a different respirator facepiece (size, style, model or make) is used, and at least annually thereafter.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(f)(3) Additional Fit Tests"]
The employer shall conduct an additional fit test whenever the employee reports, or the employer, PLHCP, supervisor, or program administrator makes visual observations of, changes in the employee's physical condition that could affect respirator fit. Such conditions include, but are not limited to, facial scarring, dental changes, cosmetic surgery, or an obvious change in body weight.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(f)(4) Selecting a Different Respirator"]
If after passing a QLFT or QNFT, the employee subsequently notifies the employer, program administrator, supervisor, or PLHCP that the fit of the respirator is unacceptable, the employee shall be given a reasonable opportunity to select a different respirator facepiece and to be retested.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(f)(5) Fit Test Protocols"]
The fit test shall be administered using an OSHA-accepted QLFT or QNFT protocol. The OSHA-accepted QLFT and QNFT protocols and procedures are contained in Appendix A of this section.[/expand]
[expand title="1910.134(f)(6) QLFT"]
QLFT may only be used to fit test negative pressure air-purifying respirators that must achieve a fit factor of 100 or less.[/expand]
[expand title="1910.134(f)(7) QNFT"]
If the fit factor, as determined through an OSHA-accepted QNFT protocol, is equal to or greater than 100 for tight-fitting half facepieces, or equal to or greater than 500 for tight-fitting full facepieces, the QNFT has been passed with that respirator.[/expand]
[expand title="1910.134(f)(8) Negative Pressure Mode"]
Fit testing of tight-fitting atmosphere-supplying respirators and tight-fitting powered air-purifying respirators shall be accomplished by performing quantitative or qualitative fit testing in the negative pressure mode, regardless of the mode of operation (negative or positive pressure) that is used for respiratory protection.

<strong>1910.134(f)(8)(i)</strong>
Qualitative fit testing of these respirators shall be accomplished by temporarily converting the respirator user's actual facepiece into a negative pressure respirator with appropriate filters, or by using an identical negative pressure air-purifying respirator facepiece with the same sealing surfaces as a surrogate for the atmosphere-supplying or powered air-purifying respirator facepiece.

<strong>1910.134(f)(8)(ii)</strong>
Quantitative fit testing of these respirators shall be accomplished by modifying the facepiece to allow sampling inside the facepiece in the breathing zone of the user, midway between the nose and mouth. This requirement shall be accomplished by installing a permanent sampling probe onto a surrogate facepiece, or by using a sampling adapter designed to temporarily provide a means of sampling air from inside the facepiece.

<strong>1910.134(f)(8)(iii)</strong>
Any modifications to the respirator facepiece for fit testing shall be completely removed, and the facepiece restored to NIOSH-approved configuration, before that facepiece can be used in the workplace.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>159</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:07:38]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:07:38]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134f-fit-testing]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(G) USE OF RESPIRATORS</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134g-use-of-respirators/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:21:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=161</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires employers to establish and implement procedures for the proper use of respirators. These requirements include prohibiting conditions that may result in facepiece seal leakage, preventing employees from removing respirators in hazardous environments, taking actions to ensure continued effective respirator operation throughout the work shift, and establishing procedures for the use of respirators in IDLH atmospheres or in interior structural firefighting situations.

[expand title="1910.134(g)(1) Facepiece Seal Protection"]
<strong>1910.134(g)(1)(i)</strong>
The employer shall not permit respirators with tight-fitting facepieces to be worn by employees who have:

<strong>1910.134(g)(1)(i)(A)</strong>
Facial hair that comes between the sealing surface of the facepiece and the face or that interferes with valve function; or

<strong>1910.134(g)(1)(i)(B)</strong>
Any condition that interferes with the face-to-facepiece seal or valve function.

<strong>1910.134(g)(1)(ii)</strong>
If an employee wears corrective glasses or goggles or other personal protective equipment, the employer shall ensure that such equipment is worn in a manner that does not interfere with the seal of the facepiece to the face of the user.

<strong>1910.134(g)(1)(iii)</strong>
For all tight-fitting respirators, the employer shall ensure that employees perform a user seal check each time they put on the respirator using the procedures in Appendix B-1 or procedures recommended by the respirator manufacturer that the employer demonstrates are as effective as those in Appendix B-1 of this section.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(g)(2) Continuing Respirator Effectiveness"]

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(i)</strong>
Appropriate surveillance shall be maintained of work area conditions and degree of employee exposure or stress. When there is a change in work area conditions or degree of employee exposure or stress that may affect respirator effectiveness, the employer shall reevaluate the continued effectiveness of the respirator.

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(ii)</strong>
The employer shall ensure that employees leave the respirator use area:

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(ii)(A)</strong>
To wash their faces and respirator facepieces as necessary to prevent eye or skin irritation associated with respirator use; or

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(ii)(B)</strong>
If they detect vapor or gas breakthrough, changes in breathing resistance, or leakage of the facepiece; or

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(ii)(C)</strong>
To replace the respirator or the filter, cartridge, or canister elements.

<strong>1910.134(g)(2)(iii)</strong>
If the employee detects vapor or gas breakthrough, changes in breathing resistance, or leakage of the facepiece, the employer must replace or repair the respirator before allowing the employee to return to the work area.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(g)(3) Procedures for IDLH Atmospheres"]
For all IDLH atmospheres, the employer shall ensure that:

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(i)</strong>
One employee or, when needed, more than one employee is located outside the IDLH atmosphere;

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(ii)</strong>
Visual, voice, or signal line communication is maintained between the employee(s) in the IDLH atmosphere and the employee(s) located outside the IDLH atmosphere;

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(iii)</strong>
The employee(s) located outside the IDLH atmosphere are trained and equipped to provide effective emergency rescue;

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(iv)</strong>
The employer or designee is notified before the employee(s) located outside the IDLH atmosphere enter the IDLH atmosphere to provide emergency rescue;

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(v)</strong>
The employer or designee authorized to do so by the employer, once notified, provides necessary assistance appropriate to the situation;

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(vi)</strong>
Employee(s) located outside the IDLH atmospheres are equipped with:

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(vi)(A)</strong>
Pressure demand or other positive pressure SCBAs, or a pressure demand or other positive pressure supplied-air respirator with auxiliary SCBA; and either

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(vi)(B)</strong>
Appropriate retrieval equipment for removing the employee(s) who enter(s) these hazardous atmospheres where retrieval equipment would contribute to the rescue of the employee(s) and would not increase the overall risk resulting from entry; or

<strong>1910.134(g)(3)(vi)(C)</strong>
Equivalent means for rescue where retrieval equipment is not required under paragraph (g)(3)(vi)(B).[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(g)(4) Interior Structural Firefighting Procedures "]
In addition to the requirements set forth under paragraph (g)(3), in interior structural fires, the employer shall ensure that:

<strong>1910.134(g)(4)(i)</strong>
At least two employees enter the IDLH atmosphere and remain in visual or voice contact with one another at all times;

<strong>1910.134(g)(4)(ii)</strong>
At least two employees are located outside the IDLH atmosphere; and

<strong>1910.134(g)(4)(iii)</strong>
All employees engaged in interior structural firefighting use SCBAs.

Note 1 to paragraph (g): One of the two individuals located outside the IDLH atmosphere may be assigned to an additional role, such as incident commander in charge of the emergency or safety officer, so long as this individual is able to perform assistance or rescue activities without jeopardizing the safety or health of any firefighter working at the incident.

Note 2 to paragraph (g): Nothing in this section is meant to preclude firefighters from performing emergency rescue activities before an entire team has assembled.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>161</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:21:11]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:21:11]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134g-use-of-respirators]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(H) MAINTENANCE AND CARE OF RESPIRATORS</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134h-maintenance-and-care-of-respirators/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:35:53 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=163</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires the employer to provide for the cleaning and disinfecting, storage, inspection, and repair of respirators used by employees.
[expand title="1910.134(h)(1) Cleaning and Disinfecting"]
The employer shall provide each respirator user with a respirator that is clean, sanitary, and in good working order. The employer shall ensure that respirators are cleaned and disinfected using the procedures in Appendix B-2 of this section, or procedures recommended by the respirator manufacturer, provided that such procedures are of equivalent effectiveness. The respirators shall be cleaned and disinfected at the following intervals:

<strong>1910.134(h)(1)(i)</strong>
Respirators issued for the exclusive use of an employee shall be cleaned and disinfected as often as necessary to be maintained in a sanitary condition;

<strong>1910.134(h)(1)(ii)</strong>
Respirators issued to more than one employee shall be cleaned and disinfected before being worn by different individuals;

<strong>1910.134(h)(1)(iii)</strong>
Respirators maintained for emergency use shall be cleaned and disinfected after each use; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(1)(iv)</strong>
Respirators used in fit testing and training shall be cleaned and disinfected after each use.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(h)(2) Storage"]
The employer shall ensure that respirators are stored as follows:

<strong>1910.134(h)(2)(i)</strong>
All respirators shall be stored to protect them from damage, contamination, dust, sunlight, extreme temperatures, excessive moisture, and damaging chemicals, and they shall be packed or stored to prevent deformation of the facepiece and exhalation valve.

<strong>1910.134(h)(2)(ii)</strong>
In addition to the requirements of paragraph (h)(2)(i) of this section, emergency respirators shall be:

<strong>1910.134(h)(2)(ii)(A)</strong>
Kept accessible to the work area;

<strong>1910.134(h)(2)(ii)(B)</strong>
Stored in compartments or in covers that are clearly marked as containing emergency respirators; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(2)(ii)(C)</strong>
Stored in accordance with any applicable manufacturer instructions.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(h)(3) Inspection"]
<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(i)</strong>
The employer shall ensure that respirators are inspected as follows:

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(i)(A)</strong>
All respirators used in routine situations shall be inspected before each use and during cleaning;

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(i)(B)</strong>
All respirators maintained for use in emergency situations shall be inspected at least monthly and in accordance with the manufacturer's recommendations, and shall be checked for proper function before and after each use; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(i)(C)</strong>
Emergency escape-only respirators shall be inspected before being carried into the workplace for use.

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(ii)</strong>
The employer shall ensure that respirator inspections include the following:

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(ii)(A)</strong>
A check of respirator function, tightness of connections, and the condition of the various parts including, but not limited to, the facepiece, head straps, valves, connecting tube, and cartridges, canisters or filters; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(ii)(B)</strong>
A check of elastomeric parts for pliability and signs of deterioration.

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(iii)</strong>
In addition to the requirements of paragraphs (h)(3)(i) and (ii) of this section, self-contained breathing apparatus shall be inspected monthly. Air and oxygen cylinders shall be maintained in a fully charged state and shall be recharged when the pressure falls to 90% of the manufacturer's recommended pressure level. The employer shall determine that the regulator and warning devices function properly.
<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(iv)</strong>
For respirators maintained for emergency use, the employer shall:

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(iv)(A)</strong>
Certify the respirator by documenting the date the inspection was performed, the name (or signature) of the person who made the inspection, the findings, required remedial action, and a serial number or other means of identifying the inspected respirator; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(3)(iv)(B)</strong>
Provide this information on a tag or label that is attached to the storage compartment for the respirator, is kept with the respirator, or is included in inspection reports stored as paper or electronic files. This information shall be maintained until replaced following a subsequent certification.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(h)(4) Repairs"]
The employer shall ensure that respirators that fail an inspection or are otherwise found to be defective are removed from service, and are discarded or repaired or adjusted in accordance with the following procedures:

<strong>1910.134(h)(4)(i)</strong>
Repairs or adjustments to respirators are to be made only by persons appropriately trained to perform such operations and shall use only the respirator manufacturer's NIOSH-approved parts designed for the respirator;

<strong>1910.134(h)(4)(ii)</strong>
Repairs shall be made according to the manufacturer's recommendations and specifications for the type and extent of repairs to be performed; and

<strong>1910.134(h)(4)(iii)</strong>
Reducing and admission valves, regulators, and alarms shall be adjusted or repaired only by the manufacturer or a technician trained by the manufacturer.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>163</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:35:53]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:35:53]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134h-maintenance-and-care-of-respirators]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(I) BREATHING AIR QUALITY AND USE</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134i-breathing-air-quality-and-use/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:44:01 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=165</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires the employer to provide employees using atmosphere-supplying respirators (supplied-air and SCBA) with breathing gases of high purity.
[expand title="1910.134(i)(1) Compressed or Liquid Air or Oxygen"]
The employer shall ensure that compressed air, compressed oxygen, liquid air, and liquid oxygen used for respiration accords with the following specifications:

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(i)</strong>
Compressed and liquid oxygen shall meet the United States Pharmacopoeia requirements for medical or breathing oxygen; and

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)</strong>
Compressed breathing air shall meet at least the requirements for Grade D breathing air described in ANSI/Compressed Gas Association Commodity Specification for Air, G-7.1-1989, to include:

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)(A)</strong>
Oxygen content (v/v) of 19.5-23.5%;

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)(B)</strong>
Hydrocarbon (condensed) content of 5 milligrams per cubic meter of air or less;

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)(C)</strong>
Carbon monoxide (CO) content of 10 ppm or less;

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)(D)</strong>
Carbon dioxide content of 1,000 ppm or less; and

<strong>1910.134(i)(1)(ii)(E)</strong>
Lack of noticeable odor.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(2) Compressed Oxygen"]
The employer shall ensure that compressed oxygen is not used in atmosphere-supplying respirators that have previously used compressed air.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(3) Oxygen Concentrations"]
The employer shall ensure that oxygen concentrations greater than 23.5% are used only in equipment designed for oxygen service or distribution.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(4) Breathing Air Cylinders"]
The employer shall ensure that cylinders used to supply breathing air to respirators meet the following requirements:

<strong>1910.134(i)(4)(i)</strong>
Cylinders are tested and maintained as prescribed in the Shipping Container Specification Regulations of the Department of Transportation (49 CFR part 180);

<strong>1910.134(i)(4)(ii)</strong>
Cylinders of purchased breathing air have a certificate of analysis from the supplier that the breathing air meets the requirements for Grade D breathing air; and

<strong>1910.134(i)(4)(iii)</strong>
The moisture content in the cylinder does not exceed a dew point of -50 deg.F (-45.6 deg.C) at 1 atmosphere pressure.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(5) Breathing Air Compressors"]
The employer shall ensure that compressors used to supply breathing air to respirators are constructed and situated so as to:

<strong>1910.134(i)(5)(i)</strong>
Prevent entry of contaminated air into the air-supply system;

<strong>1910.134(i)(5)(ii)</strong>
Minimize moisture content so that the dew point at 1 atmosphere pressure is 10 degrees F (5.56 deg.C) below the ambient temperature;

<strong>1910.134(i)(5)(iii)</strong>
Have suitable in-line air-purifying sorbent beds and filters to further ensure breathing air quality. Sorbent beds and filters shall be maintained and replaced or refurbished periodically following the manufacturer's instructions.

<strong>1910.134(i)(5)(iv)</strong>
Have a tag containing the most recent change date and the signature of the person authorized by the employer to perform the change. The tag shall be maintained at the compressor.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(6) Non-oil-lubricated Compressors"]
For compressors that are not oil-lubricated, the employer shall ensure that carbon monoxide levels in the breathing air do not exceed 10 ppm.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(7) Oil-lubricated Compressors"]
For oil-lubricated compressors, the employer shall use a high-temperature or carbon monoxide alarm, or both, to monitor carbon monoxide levels. If only high-temperature alarms are used, the air supply shall be monitored at intervals sufficient to prevent carbon monoxide in the breathing air from exceeding 10 ppm.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(8) Couplings and Air Lines"]
The employer shall ensure that breathing air couplings are incompatible with outlets for nonrespirable worksite air or other gas systems. No asphyxiating substance shall be introduced into breathing air lines.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(i)(9) Breathing-gas Containers"]
The employer shall use only the respirator manufacturer's NIOSH-approved breathing-gas containers, marked and maintained in accordance with the Quality Assurance provisions of the NIOSH approval for the SCBA as issued in accordance with the NIOSH respirator-certification standard at 42 CFR part 84.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>165</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:44:01]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:44:01]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134i-breathing-air-quality-and-use]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(J) IDENTIFICATION OF FILTERS, CARTRIDGES, AND CANISTERS</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134j-identification-of-filters-cartridges-and-canisters/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:45:59 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=168</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[The employer shall ensure that all filters, cartridges and canisters used in the workplace are labeled and color coded with the NIOSH approval label and that the label is not removed and remains legible.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>168</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:45:59]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:45:59]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134j-identification-of-filters-cartridges-and-canisters]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(K) TRAINING AND INFORMATION</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134k-training-and-information/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:50:32 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=170</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This paragraph requires the employer to provide effective training to employees who are required to use respirators. The training must be comprehensive, understandable, and recur annually, and more often if necessary. This paragraph also requires the employer to provide the basic information on respirators in Appendix D of this section to employees who wear respirators when not required by this section or by the employer to do so.
[expand title="1910.134(k)(1) Employee Knowledge"]
The employer shall ensure that each employee can demonstrate knowledge of at least the following:

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(i)</strong>
Why the respirator is necessary and how improper fit, usage, or maintenance can compromise the protective effect of the respirator;

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(ii)</strong>
What the limitations and capabilities of the respirator are;

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(iii)</strong>
How to use the respirator effectively in emergency situations, including situations in which the respirator malfunctions;

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(iv)</strong>
How to inspect, put on and remove, use, and check the seals of the respirator;

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(v)</strong>
What the procedures are for maintenance and storage of the respirator;

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(vi)</strong>
How to recognize medical signs and symptoms that may limit or prevent the effective use of respirators; and

<strong>1910.134(k)(1)(vii)</strong>
The general requirements of this section.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(k)(2) Employee Understanding"]
The training shall be conducted in a manner that is understandable to the employee.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(k)(3) Training Prior to Use"]
The employer shall provide the training prior to requiring the employee to use a respirator in the workplace.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(k)(4) Previous Training"]
An employer who is able to demonstrate that a new employee has received training within the last 12 months that addresses the elements specified in paragraph (k)(1)(i) through (vii) is not required to repeat such training provided that, as required by paragraph (k)(1), the employee can demonstrate knowledge of those element(s). Previous training not repeated initially by the employer must be provided no later than 12 months from the date of the previous training.[/expand]
[expand title="1910.134(k)(5) Retraining"]
Retraining shall be administered annually, and when the following situations occur:

<strong>1910.134(k)(5)(i)</strong>
Changes in the workplace or the type of respirator render previous training obsolete;

<strong>1910.134(k)(5)(ii)</strong>
Inadequacies in the employee's knowledge or use of the respirator indicate that the employee has not retained the requisite understanding or skill; or

<strong>1910.134(k)(5)(iii)</strong>
Any other situation arises in which retraining appears necessary to ensure safe respirator use.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(k)(6) Advisory Information"]
The basic advisory information on respirators, as presented in Appendix D of this section, shall be provided by the employer in any written or oral format, to employees who wear respirators when such use is not required by this section or by the employer.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>170</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:50:32]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:50:32]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134k-training-and-information]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(L) PROGRAM EVALUATION</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134l-program-evaluation/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:53:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=172</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This section requires the employer to conduct evaluations of the workplace to ensure that the written respiratory protection program is being properly implemented, and to consult employees to ensure that they are using the respirators properly.

[expand title="1910.134(l)(1) Workplace Evaluations"]
The employer shall conduct evaluations of the workplace as necessary to ensure that the provisions of the current written program are being effectively implemented and that it continues to be effective.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(l)(2) Program Assessment"]
The employer shall regularly consult employees required to use respirators to assess the employees' views on program effectiveness and to identify any problems. Any problems that are identified during this assessment shall be corrected. Factors to be assessed include, but are not limited to:

<strong>1910.134(l)(2)(i)</strong>
Respirator fit (including the ability to use the respirator without interfering with effective workplace performance);

<strong>1910.134(l)(2)(ii)</strong>
Appropriate respirator selection for the hazards to which the employee is exposed;

<strong>1910.134(l)(2)(iii)</strong>
Proper respirator use under the workplace conditions the employee encounters; and

<strong>1910.134(l)(2)(iv)</strong>
Proper respirator maintenance.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>172</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:53:11]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:53:11]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134l-program-evaluation]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(M) RECORDKEEPING</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134m-recordkeeping/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:56:23 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=174</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[This section requires the employer to establish and retain written information regarding medical evaluations, fit testing, and the respirator program. This information will facilitate employee involvement in the respirator program, assist the employer in auditing the adequacy of the program, and provide a record for compliance determinations by OSHA.

[expand title="1910.134(m)(1) Medical Evaluation"]
Records of medical evaluations required by this section must be retained and made available in accordance with 29 CFR 1910.1020.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(m)(2) Fit Testing"]
<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)</strong>
The employer shall establish a record of the qualitative and quantitative fit tests administered to an employee including:

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)(A)</strong>
The name or identification of the employee tested;

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)(B)</strong>
Type of fit test performed;

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)(C)</strong>
Specific make, model, style, and size of respirator tested;

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)(D)</strong>
Date of test; and

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(i)(E)</strong>
The pass/fail results for QLFTs or the fit factor and strip chart recording or other recording of the test results for QNFTs.

<strong>1910.134(m)(2)(ii)</strong>
Fit test records shall be retained for respirator users until the next fit test is administered.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(m)(3) Copy of Program"]
A written copy of the current respirator program shall be retained by the employer.[/expand]

[expand title="1910.134(m)(4) Material for Employees"]
Written materials required to be retained under this paragraph shall be made available upon request to affected employees and to the Assistant Secretary or designee for examination and copying.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>174</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:56:23]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:56:23]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134m-recordkeeping]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(N) EFFECTIVE DATE</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134n-effective-date/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 20:57:06 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=176</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Paragraphs (d)(3)(i)(A) and (d)(3)(i)(B) of this section become effective November 22, 2006.]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>176</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:57:06]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 20:57:06]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134n-effective-date]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>1910.134(O) APPENDICES</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/1910-134o-appendices/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 21:03:04 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=178</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[Compliance with Appendix A, Appendix B-1, Appendix B-2, Appendix C, and Appendix D to this section are mandatory.
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>178</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:03:04]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:03:04]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[1910-134o-appendices]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="osha-standards"><![CDATA[OSHA Standards]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Acronyms</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/acronyms/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 21:14:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=184</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="ACGIH"]
American Conference of Governmental Industrial Hygienists[/expand]
[expand title="AIHA"]
American Industrial Hygiene Association[/expand]
[expand title="ANSI"]
American National Standards Institute[/expand]
[expand title="APF"]
The Assigned Protection Factor (APF) indicates the workplace level of respiratory protection that a respirator or class of respirators is expected to provide to employees when the employer implements a continuing, effective respiratory protection program as specified by this section.[/expand]
[expand title="APR"]
An air-purifying respirator (APR) is a respirator with an air-purifying filter, cartridge, or canister that removes specific air contaminants by passing ambient air through the air-purifying element.[/expand]
[expand title="Ci"]
Concentration Inside. The concentration measured inside the respirator facepiece[/expand]
[expand title="Co"]
Concentration Outside. Concentration measured outside the respirator.[/expand]
[expand title="DFM"]
A Dust, Fume, and Mist filter[/expand]
[expand title="DOP"]
Dioctylphthalate, which is an aerosolized agent used for quantitative fit testing.[/expand]
[expand title="EPF"]
A Effective Protection Factor (EPF) study is a study, conducted in the workplace, that measures the protection provided by a properly selected, fit-tested, and functioning respirator when used intermittently for only some fraction of the total workplace exposure time (i.e., sampling is conducted during periods when respirators are worn and not worn). EPFs are not directly comparable to Workplace Protection Factor (WPF) values because the determinations include both the time spent in contaminated atmospheres with and without respiratory protection; therefore, EPFs usually underestimate the protection afforded by a respirator that is used continuously in the workplace.[/expand]
[expand title="HEPA"]
A High Efficiency Particulate Air (HEPA) filter is a filter that is at least 99.97% efficient in removing monodispersed particles of 0.3 micrometers in diameter. The equivalent NIOSH 42 CFR 84 particulate filters are the N100, R100, and P100 filters.[/expand]
[expand title="IDLH"]
Immediately Dangerous to Life or Health. An atmosphere that poses an immediate threat to life, would cause irreversible adverse health effects, or would impair an individual’s ability to escape from a dangerous atmosphere.[/expand]
[expand title="LANL"]
Los Alamos National Laboratory[/expand]
[expand title="LASL"]
Los Alamos Scientific Laboratory[/expand]
[expand title="LLNL"]
Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory[/expand]
[expand title="MSHA"]
Mine Safety and Health Administration[/expand]
[expand title="MUC"]
Maximum Use Concentration (MUC) is the maximum atmospheric concentration of a hazardous substance from which an employee can be expected to be protected when wearing a respirator, and is determined by the assigned protection factor of the respirator or class of respirators and the exposure limit of the hazardous substance. The MUC can be determined mathematically by multiplying the assigned protection factor specified for a respirator by the required OSHA permissible exposure limit, short-term exposure limit, or ceiling limit. When no OSHA exposure limit is available for a hazardous substance, an employer must determine an MUC on the basis of relevant available information and informed professional judgment.[/expand]
[expand title="NFPA"]
National Fire Protection Association[/expand]
[expand title="NIOSH"]
National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health[/expand]
[expand title="NRC"]
Nuclear Regulatory Commission[/expand]
[expand title="OSHA"]
Occupational Safety and Health Administration[/expand]
[expand title="OSH Act"]
The Occupational Safety and Health Act of 1970 (29 U.S.C. 655, 657, 665).[/expand]
[expand title="PAPR"]
A Powered Air-Purifying Respirator (PARP) is an air-purifying respirator that uses a blower to force the ambient air through air-purifying elements to the inlet covering.[/expand]
[expand title="PEL"]
Permissible Exposure Limit. An occupational exposure limit specified by OSHA.[/expand]
[expand title="PPF"]
A Program Protection Factor (PPF) study is a study that determines the protection provided by a respirator during use. This determination generally is accomplished by measuring the ratio of the concentration of an airborne contaminant (e.g., hazardous substance) outside the respirator (Co) to the concentration inside the respirator (Ci) (i.e., Co/Ci). Therefore, as the ratio between Co and Ci increases, the protection factor increases, indicating an increase in the level of protection provided to employees by the respirator. There are four types of protection factor studies: EPF, PPF, WPF, and SWPF.[/expand]
[expand title="QLFT"]
A Qualitative Fit Test (QLFT) is a pass/fail fit test to assess the adequacy of respirator fit that relies on the individual’s response to the test agent.[/expand]
[expand title="QNFT"]
A Quantitative Fit Test (QNFT) is an assessment of the adequacy of respirator fit by numerically measuring the amount of leakage into the respirator.[/expand]
[expand title="RDL"]
Respirator Decision Logic. Respirator selection guidance developed by NIOSH that contains a set of respirator protection factors.[/expand]
[expand title="REL"]
Recommended Exposure Limit. An occupational exposure level recommended by NIOSH.[/expand]
[expand title="SAR"]
A Supplied-Air (or Airline) Respirator (SAR) is an atmosphere-supplying respirator for which the source of breathing air is not designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]
[expand title="SCBA"]
A Self-Contained Breathing Apparatus (SCBA) is an atmosphere- supplying respirator for which the breathing air source is designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]
[expand title="SWPF"]
A Simulated Workplace Protection Factor (SWPF) study is a study, conducted in a controlled laboratory setting and in which Co and Ci sampling is performed while the respirator user performs a series of set exercises. The laboratory setting is used to control many of the variables found in workplace studies, while the exercises simulate the work activities of respirator users. This type of study is designed to determine the optimum performance of respirators by reducing the impact of sources of variability through maintenance of tightly controlled study conditions.[/expand]
[expand title="TLV"]
Threshold Limit Value. An occupational exposure level recommended by ACGIH.[/expand]
[expand title="TWA"]
Time-Weighted Average is used to measure a worker's daily exposure to hazardous substances, averaged on an 8-hour workday. The average is calculated from air samples throughout a work cycle and the amount of time spent working in those conditions. OSHA uses TWAs to establish Permissible Exposure Limits for the contaminants encountered in industries.
The TWA is calculated in units of parts per million (ppm) or mg/m3.[/expand]
[expand title="WPF"]
A Workplace Protection Factor (WPF) study is a study, conducted under actual conditions of use in the workplace, that measures the protection provided by a properly selected, fit-tested, and functioning respirator, when the respirator is worn correctly and used as part of a comprehensive respirator program that is in compliance with OSHA’s Respiratory Protection standard at 29 CFR 1910.134. Measurements of Co and Ci are obtained only while the respirator is being worn during performance of normal work tasks (i.e., samples are not collected when the respirator is not being worn). As the degree of protection afforded by the respirator increases, the WPF increases.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>184</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:14:08]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:14:08]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[acronyms]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="acronyms"><![CDATA[Acronyms]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Glossary</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/glossary/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 21:23:22 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=186</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[[expand title="Air-purifying respirator (APR)"]
A respirator with an air-purifying filter, cartridge, or canister that removes specific air contaminants by passing ambient air through the air-purifying element.[/expand]

[expand title="Assigned protection factor (APF)"]
An assigned protection factor indicates the workplace level of respiratory protection that a respirator or class of respirators is expected to provide to employees when the employer implements a continuing, effective respiratory protection program as specified by this section.[/expand]

[expand title="Atmosphere-supplying respirator (ASR)"]
A respirator that supplies the respirator user with breathing air from a source independent of the ambient atmosphere, and includes SARs and SCBA units.[/expand]

[expand title="Canister or cartridge"]
A container with a filter, sorbent, or catalyst, or combination of these items, which removes specific contaminants from the air passed through the container.[/expand]

[expand title="Continuous flow respirator"]
An atmosphere-supplying respirator that provides a continuous flow of breathable air to the respirator facepiece.[/expand]

[expand title="Demand respirator"]
An atmosphere-supplying respirator that admits breathing air to the facepiece only when a negative pressure is created inside the facepiece by inhalation.[/expand]

[expand title="Dioctylphthalate (DOP)"]
An aerosolized agent used for quantitative fit testing.[/expand]

[expand title="Elastomeric"]
A respirator facepiece made of a natural or synthetic elastic material such as natural rubber, silicone, or synthetic rubber.[/expand]

[expand title="Emergency situation"]
Any occurrence such as, but not limited to, equipment failure, rupture of containers, or failure of control equipment that may or does result in an uncontrolled significant release of an airborne contaminant.[/expand]

[expand title="Employee exposure"]
Exposure to a concentration of an airborne contaminant that would occur if the employee were not using respiratory protection.[/expand]

[expand title="End-of-service-life indicator (ESLI)"]
A system that warns the respirator user of the approach of the end of adequate respiratory protection, for example, that the sorbent is approaching saturation or is no longer effective.[/expand]

[expand title="Escape-only respirator"]
A respirator intended to be used only for emergency exit.[/expand]

[expand title="Filter or air-purifying element"]
A component used in respirators to remove solid or liquid aerosols from the inspired air.[/expand]

[expand title="Filtering facepiece (or dust mask)"]
A negative pressure particulate respirator with a filter as an integral part of the facepiece or with the entire facepiece composed of the filtering medium.[/expand]

[expand title="Fit factor"]
A quantitative estimate of the fit of a particular respirator to a specific individual, and typically estimates the ratio of the concentration of a substance in ambient air to its concentration inside the respirator when worn.[/expand]

[expand title="Fit test"]
The use of a protocol to qualitatively or quantitatively evaluate the fit of a respirator on an individual.[/expand]

[expand title="Helmet"]
A rigid respiratory inlet covering that also provides head protection against impact and penetration.[/expand]

[expand title="High-efficiency particulate air filter (HEPA)"]
A filter that is at least 99.97% efficient in removing monodispersed particles of 0.3 micrometers in diameter. The equivalent NIOSH 42 CFR 84 particulate filters are the N100, R100, and P100 filters.[/expand]

[expand title="Hood"]
A respiratory inlet covering that completely covers the head and neck and may also cover portions of the shoulders and torso.[/expand]

[expand title="Immediately dangerous to life or health (IDLH)"]
An atmosphere that poses an immediate threat to life, would cause irreversible adverse health effects, or would impair an individual’s ability to escape from a dangerous atmosphere.[/expand]

[expand title="Interior structural firefighting"]
The physical activity of fire suppression, rescue or both, inside of buildings or enclosed structures which are involved in a fire situation beyond the incipient stage. (See 29 CFR 1910.155).[/expand]

[expand title="Loose-fitting facepiece"]
A respiratory inlet covering that is designed to form a partial seal with the face.[/expand]

[expand title="Maximum use concentration (MUC)"]
The maximum atmospheric concentration of a hazardous substance from which an employee can be expected to be protected when wearing a respirator, and is determined by the assigned protection factor of the respirator or class of respirators and the exposure limit of the hazardous substance. The MUC can be determined mathematically by multiplying the assigned protection factor specified for a respirator by the required OSHA permissible exposure limit, short-term exposure limit, or ceiling limit. When no OSHA exposure limit is available for a hazardous substance, an employer must determine an MUC on the basis of relevant available information and informed professional judgment.[/expand]

[expand title="Negative pressure respirator (tight-fitting)"]
A respirator in which the air pressure inside the facepiece is negative during inhalation with respect to the ambient air pressure outside the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Oxygen deficient atmosphere"]
An atmosphere with an oxygen content below 19.5% by volume.[/expand]

[expand title="Permissible Exposure Limit (PEL)"]
An occupational exposure limit specified by OSHA.[/expand]

[expand title="Physician or other licensed healthcare professional (PLHCP)"]
An individual whose legally permitted scope of practice (i.e., license, registration, or certification) allows him or her to independently provide, or be delegated the responsibility to provide, some or all of the healthcare services required by paragraph (e) of this section.[/expand]

[expand title="Positive pressure respirator"]
A respirator in which the pressure inside the respiratory inlet covering exceeds the ambient air pressure outside the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Powered air-purifying respirator (PAPR)"]
An air-purifying respirator that uses a blower to force the ambient air through air-purifying elements to the inlet covering.[/expand]

[expand title="Pressure demand respirator"]
A positive pressure atmosphere-supplying respirator that admits breathing air to the facepiece when the positive pressure is reduced inside the facepiece by inhalation.[/expand]

[expand title="Protection factor study"]
A study that determines the protection provided by a respirator during use. This determination generally is accomplished by measuring the ratio of the concentration of an airborne contaminant (e.g., hazardous substance) outside the respirator (Co) to the concentration inside the respirator (Ci) (i.e., Co/Ci). Therefore, as the ratio between Co and Ci increases, the protection factor increases, indicating an increase in the level of protection provided to employees by the respirator. There are four types of protection factor studies: EPF, PPF, WPF, and SWPF.[/expand]

[expand title="Effective Protection Factor (EPF) study"]
A study, conducted in the workplace, that measures the protection provided by a properly selected, fit-tested, and functioning respirator when used intermittently for only some fraction of the total workplace exposure time (i.e., sampling is conducted during periods when respirators are worn and not worn). EPFs are not directly comparable to Workplace Protection Factor (WPF) values because the determinations include both the time spent in contaminated atmospheres with and without respiratory protection; therefore, EPFs usually underestimate the protection afforded by a respirator that is used continuously in the workplace.[/expand]

[expand title="Program Protection Factor (PPF) study"]
A study that estimates the protection provided by a respirator within a specific respirator program. Like the EPF, it is focused not only on the respirator’s performance, but also the effectiveness of the complete respirator program. PPFs are affected by all factors of the program, including respirator selection and maintenance, user training and motivation, work activities and program administration.[/expand]

[expand title="Workplace Protection Factor (WPF) study"]
A study, conducted under actual conditions of use in the workplace, that measures the protection provided by a properly selected, fit-tested, and functioning respirator, when the respirator is worn correctly and used as part of a comprehensive respirator program that is in compliance with OSHA’s Respiratory Protection standard at 29 CFR 1910.134. Measurements of Co and Ci are obtained only while the respirator is being worn during performance of normal work tasks (i.e., samples are not collected when the respirator is not being worn). As the degree of protection afforded by the respirator increases, the WPF increases.[/expand]

[expand title="Simulated Workplace Protection Factor (SWPF) study"]
A study, conducted in a controlled laboratory setting and in which Co and Ci sampling is performed while the respirator user performs a series of set exercises. The laboratory setting is used to control many of the variables found in workplace studies, while the exercises simulate the work activities of respirator users. This type of study is designed to determine the optimum performance of respirators by reducing the impact of sources of variability through maintenance of tightly controlled study conditions.[/expand]

[expand title="Qualitative fit test (QLFT)"]
A pass/fail fit test to assess the adequacy of respirator fit that relies on the individual’s response to the test agent.[/expand]

[expand title="Quantitative fit test (QNFT)"]
An assessment of the adequacy of respirator fit by numerically measuring the amount of leakage into the respirator.[/expand]

[expand title="Recommended Exposure Limit (REL)"]
An occupational exposure level recommended by NIOSH.[/expand]

[expand title="Respirator Decision Logic (RDL)"]
Respirator selection guidance developed by NIOSH that contains a set of respirator protection factors.[/expand]

[expand title="Respiratory inlet covering"]
That portion of a respirator that forms the protective barrier between the user’s respiratory tract and an air-purifying device or breathing air source, or both. It may be a facepiece, helmet, hood, suit, or a mouthpiece respirator with nose clamp.[/expand]

[expand title="Self-contained breathing apparatus (SCBA)"]
An atmosphere- supplying respirator for which the breathing air source is designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]

[expand title="Supplied-air respirator (or airline) respirator (SAR)"]
An atmosphere-supplying respirator for which the source of breathing air is not designed to be carried by the user.[/expand]

[expand title="Threshold Limit Value (TLV)"]
An occupational exposure level recommended by ACGIH.[/expand]

[expand title="Tight-fitting facepiece"]
A respiratory inlet covering that forms a complete seal with the face.[/expand]

[expand title="Time-weighted average (TWA)"]
Time-Weighted Average is used to measure a worker's daily exposure to hazardous substances, averaged on an 8-hour workday. The average is calculated from air samples throughout a work cycle and the amount of time spent working in those conditions. OSHA uses TWAs to establish Permissible Exposure Limits for the contaminants encountered in industries.
The TWA is calculated in units of parts per million (ppm) or mg/m3.[/expand]

[expand title="User seal check"]
An action conducted by the respirator user to determine if the respirator is properly seated to the face.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>186</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:23:22]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:23:22]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[glossary]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="glossary"><![CDATA[Glossary]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
		<title>Resources</title>
		<link>http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/2017/11/13/resources/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 13 Nov 2017 21:30:15 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Livvy]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://respirators101.iuoe-hazmat.com/?p=188</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[For assistance, contact us. We are OSHA. We can help. It’s confidential.

[expand title="Contacting OSHA"]
To get a list of OSHA publications, to ask questions or to get more information, to contact OSHA’s free consultation service, or to file a confidential complaint, contact
OSHA at 1-800-321-OSHA (6742)
(TTY) 1-877-889-5627
or visit www.osha.gov[/expand]

[expand title="Small Businesses"]
OSHA offers free consultation to qualifying small- and medium-sized businesses to help recognize hazards, suggest approaches to solving problems and identifying the kinds of help available if further assistance is required.
Visit <a href="https://www.osha.gov/dcsp/smallbusiness/index.html">https://www.osha.gov/dcsp/smallbusiness/index.html</a> for information on compliance assistance and consultation programs.
In addition, the OSHA Small Entity Compliance Guide provides procedures and checklists that can help small businesses comply with the respirator standard. This information can be accessed at: <a href="https://www.osha.gov/Publications/3384small-entity-for-respiratory-protection-standard-rev.pdf">https://www.osha.gov/Publications/3384small-entity-for-respiratory-protection-standard-rev.pdf</a>[/expand]

[expand title="Cartridge Change Schedules"]
OSHA provides information on determining respirator cartridge change schedules <a href="https://www.osha.gov/SLTC/etools/respiratory/change_schedule.html">https://www.osha.gov/SLTC/etools/respiratory/change_schedule.html</a>[/expand]

[expand title="Respirator Programs"]
Detailed information on respirator programs can be accessed at
<a href="http://www.osha.gov/SLTC/etools/respiratory">http://www.osha.gov/SLTC/etools/respiratory</a>[/expand]

[expand title="Compliance Assistance Specialists"]
OSHA has compliance assistance specialists throughout the nation who can provide information to employers and workers about OSHA standards, short educational programs on specific hazards or OSHA rights and responsibilities, and information on additional compliance assistance resources. Contact your local OSHA office for more information.[/expand]

[expand title="OSHA Publications"]
OSHA’s extensive publications help explain OSHA standards, job hazards, and mitigation strategies and provide assistance in developing effective injury and illness prevention programs. For a listing of free publications, visit www.osha.gov or call 1-800-321-OSHA (6742).[/expand]

[expand title="Quick Takes"]
OSHA’s free, twice-monthly online newsletter, QuickTakes, offers the latest news about OSHA initiatives and products to assist employers and workers in finding and preventing workplace hazards. To sign up for QuickTakes, visit OSHA’s website at www.osha.gov and click on QuickTakes at the top of the page.[/expand]]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>188</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:30:15]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2017-11-13 21:30:15]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[open]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[resources]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="resources"><![CDATA[Resources]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_edit_last]]></wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[3]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
</channel>
</rss>
